Guide to the Mussolini Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mussolini collection of V. Lada-Mocarski
1937-1949
MS 812
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(1 box, 1 folio)
Correspondence, manuscript drafts, photographs and research materials for an article, "The last three days of Mussolini," written by Valerian Lada-Mocarski (1898-1971) and published in the Atlantic Monthly, December 1945. The papers include copies of the article.
Lada-Mocarski, Valerian, 1898-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. V. Lada-Mocarski, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of research notes, manuscript drafts, correspondence, photographs and printed material about the days just prior to and after the execution of Mussolini in April of 1945, assembled by V. Lada-Mocarski for a magazine article, "The Last Three Days of Mussolini," Atlantic Monthly, December 1945. In 1945 Mr. Lada-Mocarski was in the O.S.S. in Switzerland and was granted permission to enter Italy right after the execution. He was able to obtain many eyewitness accounts.
World War, 1939-1945; Europe; Authors; Lada-Mocarski, Valerian, 1898-1971; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945
- Inventory
  - Manuscript
    - "The Last Three Days of Mussolini" from the Atlantic Monthly, 3 copies, 1945 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Last Three Days of Mussolini" from the Atlantic Monthly, 2 xerox copies, 1945 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Research Files
    - Notes, 2 notebooks, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reports on the Division, 1945 April 9-19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reports on the Partisans, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Interviews with eyewitnesses, 1945 April-Jun, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Detailed account on events... Il Capitano di Fregata, 1945 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Composites of last days and execution, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Liberty blooms in Tremezzina, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Autopsy reports on Mussolini, 1945 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Autopsy report on Henry Harrisson, 1943 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript drafts
    - "Last Days of Mussolini and His Ministers", [1945] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Last Days of Mussolini and His Ministers", [1945] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "The Last Three Days of Mussolini", [1945] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence
    - Before publication, 1945 April-May (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Before publication, 1945 October 31-November 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - After publication, 1945 November 27-1946 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - After publication, 1949 October 7-1948 March 30, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs
    - P-1 Mocarski, partisans and reprisal scenes, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - P-2 Mostly Como after "Liberation", [1945] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - P-3 Valla and partisans near Como where he worked out of Lugano, Switzerland, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - P-4 With Valla, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - P-5 Where Mussolini and Petacci were shot, 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - P-6 Unidentified groups, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - P-7 Public display after execution, 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Memorabilia
    - Passports, foreign exchange, luggage stickers, etc. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Printed
    - I C.L.N Nell'Alta Italia, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Guerra di Liberazione, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Empty Balcony, Pietro Saporiti, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Clippings, 1946, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "What Happened to Mussolini's Millions" by Edmund Palmieri and John Kobler, [1949?] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Printed matter (oversize)
    - Clippings from Avanti!, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Clippings from Giornale Lombardo, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Clippings from Il Popolo, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Clippings from L'Italia Liberta, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Clippings from La Libertà, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Clippings from L'Unità, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Clippings from other newspapers, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Broadside
    - "Con L'Approvazione...", 1945 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Maps
    - Map of Switzerland, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Topographical map of the Como District, Italy, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)